Guide to the Peter Parker Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Peter Parker collection
1825-1947
1825-1884
Ms Coll 6
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
6
(11 boxes)
Peter Parker graduated from Yale College in 1831 and from the Medical Institution of Yale College in 1834. Ordained as a Presbyterian minister in 1834, he sailed that year to China as the first Protestant medical missionary to that country. The papers relate to Parker's medical practice at the Canton Hospital and elsewhere, his missionary activities including his sermons, and his work for the U.S. Government as a diplomat to China. Most of the papers have been photographed at http://cushing.med.yale.edu/greenstone/collect/pppapers/ Use in conjunction with this finding aid.
Parker, Peter, 1804-1888
Lam, Qua
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Manuscripts were donated by Peter Parker of Barrington, Illinois, May 16, 1960. Portraits and urinary calculi donated in the late nineteenth century by Peter Parker to the Medical School through Moses C. White, professor of pathology and a former missionary to China. These were later transferred by the Medical School to the Historical Library. Some materials, including photographs, were donated in 1966 by Mrs. William W. Cadbury, widow of an early twentieth century medical missionary to Canton.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Journals also available on microfilm. Most items have been digitized. Patrons may be requested to use these surrogates.
Associated Materials
The Library holds over 80 oil paintings by Lam Qua of Peter Parker's patients with large tumors. They were sent to the Medical School by Mrs. Harriet Parker in 1890 (see Correspondence under Herbert E. Smith, Box 1, Folder 20). They are represented in the Cushing/Whiney Medical Library Digital Library. See http://library.medicine.yale.edu/find/digital.
Biographical / Historical
Peter Parker, medical missionary and diplomat to China, was born in Framingham, Massachusetts on June 18, 1804. His parents, Nathan and Catherine Parker, were farmers and devout followers of the orthodox Congregational faith. He attended Amherst College and then transferred to Yale College in 1830. After graduation in 1831, Parker studied both theology and medicine and was awarded an M.D. from Yale in 1834. In January 1834 he was ordained to the Presbyterian ministry in Philadelphia and, under the auspices of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, he departed a month later for Canton as the first Protestant medical missionary to China. With assistance from American and British benefactors, he opened the Ophthalmic Hospital at Canton in 1835. Parker specialized in treating diseases of the eyes, especially cataracts, but also performed general surgery including the removal of large tumors, and lithotomies. In 1847, he became the first physician to introduce anesthesia to China. With the onset of the Opium War (1840-1842), Parker returned to America in 1840, where he sought financial support for his hospital in the United States and Europe. In Washington, D.C., he met with government officials and urged the sending of an envoy to China. He met and married Harriet Colby Webster in 1841. In 1842, Parker resumed his medical missionary practice at Canton and became involved in diplomatic relations between America and China. In 1844 he served as translator and assistant under Caleb Cushing, U.S. Attorney General, and participated in negotiating the first treaty between the two countries, the Treaty of Wanghia. Dismissed by the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in 1847 because the Board doubted the utility of medical missionaries, Parker continued his hospital until 1855 while acting as a part-time member of the American Legation. Due to a prolonged illness, Parker returned to the United States in 1855 only to sail back to China later that year as American Commissioner to China. Recalled by the U.S. government in 1857, Parker and his wife settled in Washington, D.C., where he was active in organizations such as the Evangelical Alliance for the United States of America and the Board of Regents of the Smithsonian Institution. His only child, Peter Parker, was born in 1859. The Rev. Peter Parker died on January 10, 1888.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes Parker's letters to his family beginning in 1825, instructions from the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, many letters from Sir John Bowring, British consul at Canton and later governor of Hong Kong, and other correspondence relating to Parker's medical, missionary, diplomatic, and personal affairs. Writings include handwritten sermons and addresses. Medical reports and ledgers include Parker's handwritten quarterly reports of Canton Hospital, which contain lengthy case reports on a selection of surgeries. Two volumes of ledgers list patients treated at Canton Hospital with their diagnoses, and another ledger relates to Parker's private medical practice. Images include the buildings and staff of the Canton hospital and lantern slides of patients with large tumors, all dating from after Parker's time. The collection also includes miscellanea, memorabilia, and a box of preserved urinary calculi removed by Parker from patients in the hospital. Associated with the collection are over 80 oil portraits of Peter Parker's patients with noticeable tumors by Western-trained Chinese artist Lam Qua. Most of the Peter Parker Collection has been photographed. See http://cushing.med.yale.edu/greenstone/collect/pppapers/ Use in conjunction with this finding aid. The associated Lam Qua portraits of Peter Parker's patients are online at http://cushing.med.yale.edu/gsdl/collect/ppdcdot/
Arrangement
Organized into seven series: 1. Correspondence. 2. Journals. 3 Sermons, addresses, and other writings. 4. Medical reports and ledgers. 5. Miscellaneous. 6. Photographs, 7. Urinary calculi.
Anesthesia -- China; Hospitals -- China; Missionaries, Medical -- China; Ophthalmology; Surgery; Urinary organs -- Calculi; Diaries; Lantern slides; Medical records; Photographs; Sermons; Physicians; Surgeons; Missionaries, Medical; Diplomats; Parker, Peter, 1804-1888; Parker, Harriet Colby Webster; Bowring, John, 1792-1872; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868; Cadbury, William Warder, 1877-1959; Cushing, Caleb, 1800-1879; Klaproth, Julius von, 1783-1835; Lam, Qua; White, Moses Clark, 1819-1900; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions; Canton Hospital (Guangzhou, China); Congressional Temperance Society (Washington, D.C.); Evangelical Alliance for the United States of America; Medical Missionary Society in China; Smithsonian Institution; United States. Department of State; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1831; Yale College (1718-1887). Medical Institution. Class of 1834; Amherst College
- Correspondence, 1.
  Arrangement
  Special correspondence followed by correspondence in alphabetical order.
  - Parker, Peter to his family and related letters, 1825-1836 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Peter Parker's father, Nathan Parker, died in 1826. Letters afterward are to his mother Catherine and his sister Catherine in Framingham, Massachusetts. Included in the folder are letters written to Parker's mother as Parker was sailing to China, and a letter about Parker that came into family hands.
    - To parents, 1825 January 2
    - To parents and sister Catherine, 1826 January 1
    - To parents, 1826 April 16
    - To parents, 1826 May 17
    - To parents, 1826 July 21
    - To mother and sister, 1826 October 15
    - To mother, 1826 November 9
    - To mother, 1834 June 4
    - P. Perit to Mrs. Catherine Parker, 1834 June 4
      On Peter Parker's sailing for China on the Ship Morrison. Peter Parker had spent some weeks with Perit and his wife before the departure.
    - James C. Richmond to Mrs. Catherine Parker, 1834 June 9
      On Peter Parker's sailing for China.
    - A. B. Haile, New Haven, to his sister, Miss Abigail Bent, Framingham, 1834 September 26
      On Peter Parker. Ashbel B. Haile graduated from Yale College in 1835.
  - Parker, Peter, to his family, 1837-1848 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letters to his mother and younger brothers, his sister Catherine, and his married sister Maria Fay.
    - To mother, sisters, and brothers, 1837 April 2
    - To mother and sister, 1837 May 5
    - To mother, sisters, and brothers, 1837 July 15
    - To sister Catherine, 1837 July 29
    - To mother, sisters, and brothers, 1837 October 3
    - To sister Maria Fay, 1837 November 20
    - To sister Maria Fay, 1843 February 26
    - To sister Maria Fay, 1843 March 12
    - To Abijah and Maria Fay, 1848 December 26
  - "Instructions of the Prudential Committee of the Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missionaries to the Rev. Peter Parker, M.D.", 1834 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    These are the detailed missionary instructions given to Peter Parker before he sailed for China.
  - Caleb Cushing, Macao, to Peter Parker, 1844 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Appointing Parker Secretary to the U.S. mission in China
  - Peter Parker to the Prudential Committee of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1846 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Parker's copies of three letters in January 1846 defending the importance of medicine to foreign missionary work.
    - Peter Parker to the Prudential Committee, 1846 January 1
    - Peter Parker to the Prudential Committee, 1846 January 22
    - Peter Parker to the Prudential Committee, 1846 January 31
  - Isaac Bull, et al, Canton, to Peter Parker Parker, 1846 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Describes an uprising of peasants in Canton against Western interests. Signed by twenty-six people.
  - John Bowring, Hong Kong, to Peter Parker, 1852-1856 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sir John Bowring, British consul at Canton and later governor of Hong Kong, corresponded with Parker frequently.
    - Bowring to Parker, 1850 February 11
    - Bowring to Parker, 1852 May 8
    - Bowring to Parker, 1852 June 10
    - Bowring to Parker, 1852 June 19
    - Bowring to Parker, 1852 October
    - Bowring to Parker, 1853 January 6
    - Bowring to Parker, 1853 February 9
    - Bowring to Parker, 1853 October 28
    - Edith Alice Bowring to Mrs. Harriet Parker, 1855 April 6
    - Bowring to Parker, 1855 October 30
    - Bowring to Parker, 1855 December 31
    - Parker to Bowring (copy) "Confidential", 1856 April 6
    - Bowring to Parker, 1856 April 7
    - Bowring to Parker, 1856 April 22
    - Bowring to Parker, 1856 May 24
      For more letters from 1856, see folder 9.
  - John Bowring to Peter Parker, 1857-1871 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bowring to Parker, 1857 January 5
    - Bowring to Parker, 1857 January 16
    - Bowring to Parker, 1857 January 18
    - Bowring to Parker, 1857 April 29
    - Bowring to Parker, 1857 May 5
    - Bowring to Parker, 1857 June 22
    - Bowring to Parker, 1857 June 30
    - Bowring to Parker, 1857 July 5
    - Bowring to Parker, 1857 October 15
    - Bowring to Parker, 1858 February 14
    - Bowring to Parker, 1858 April 13
    - Bowring to Parker, 1858 May 17
    - Bowring to Parker, 1858 June 3
    - Bowring to Mrs. Harriet Parker, 1871 January 3
    - Bowring to Parker, 1871 July 1
    - Bowring to Mrs. Harriet Parker, 1871 July 11
    - Bowring to Parker, n.d.
  - John Bowring fragments and autographs collected by Peter Parker, 1856-1857 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Parker (or possibly someone later) cut a number of letters received from Bowring, sometimes leaving sizeable fragments including the signature, or sometimes only the signature. Dated fragments precede undated fragments and signatures.
    - Bowring fragment, 1856 March 7
    - Bowring fragment, 1856 March 13
    - Bowring fragment, 1856 April 9
    - Bowring fragment, 1856 May 2
    - Bowring fragment, 1856 May 28
    - Bowring fragment, 1856 October 17
    - Bowring fragment, 1856 October 23
    - Bowring fragment, 1856 December 18
    - Bowring fragment, 1856 December 24
    - Bowring fragment, 1857 May
    - Bowring fragment, 1857 May 27
    - Bowring fragment, 1857 August 3
    - Bowring fragment, 1857
    - Bowring fragment, undated 1
    - Bowring fragment, undated 2
    - Bowring fragment, undated 3
    - Bowring fragment, undated 4
    - Bowring fragment, undated 5
    - Bowring fragment, undated 6
    - Bowring signatures, n.d.
  - Authorization for Parker Parker to draw his salary as Commissioner to China (duplicate), 1855 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Signed by Secertary of State, George L. Marcy.
  - Peter Parker's announcement of the birth of his son, 1859 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    The Parkers had only one child, Peter Parker, born in 1859.
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1847, 1869-1888 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    In 1868, Peter Parker was named a member of the Board of Regents of the Smithsonian Institution. See also letters from Joseph Henry and William T. Sherman in Box 1, folders17 and 21.
    - Report of the Organization Committee of the Smithsonian Institution (Washington, D.C., 1847)
      Peter Parker's copy.
    - Chief Justice Salmon P. Chase to Peter Parker, 1869 April 14
      On meeting with members of the National Academy of Sciences.
    - Joseph Henry to Peter Parker, 1876 January 20
      Physicist Joseph Henry was the first Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution.
    - General William T. Sherman to Peter Parker, 1883 January 9
    - George Bancroft to Peter Parker, n.d.
    - S. P. Langley, Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution, to Mrs. Harriet Parker, 1888 January 13
      Includes resolution, dated January 11, on Peter Parker's death.
  - "Copy of a translation into Chinese of the President's letter to the Emperor", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    President John Tyler wrote a letter to the Emperor, sent with Caleb Cushing in 1844. A later U.S. president also wrote to the Emperor.
  - Materials related to Julius Klaproth, 1824-1833 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    These materials were sent to Parker by Major Benjamin Perley Poore. Julius Heinrich Klaproth (1783-1835) was a German linguist, Orientalist, historian, and author. The materials include letters to Klaproth written in German and Chinese, and said to be about the Chinese language.
  - Correspondence, A-D (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Abercrombie, John, Edinburgh, to Dr. [Thomas] Sewall, 1843 September 16
      See Sewall below.
    - Bourboulon, A., to Peter Parker, 1857 March 7
    - [Buchanan] Peter Parker to James Buchanan (copy), 1846 June 22
    - Buchanan, James, to Peter Parker (copy), 1847 November 10
      Includes copy of letter January 28, 1847. Concerning his appointment as interim charge d'affairs of the Chinese mission of the U.S. Government.
    - C., W., Canton, to Dr. James Cooper, Junr., New Castle, Delaware, 1838 January 31
      Discusses a Dr. Parker's Chinese patient with a large butock, who is as yet afraid to undergo an operation. W.C. mentions enclosing a sketch which is not present. The description appears to correspond with the Lam Qua portrait of Wang Keking, Portrait No. 67. A transcript is included. This letter may have come to the Historical Library independently of materials donated by the Parker family.
    - Chase, S[almon] P., to Peter Parker, 1864 December 16
    - Choate, Rufus, to Peter Parker, 1856 October 10
    - Choate, Rufus, to Mrs. Dr. [Harvey] Lindsly
      Mrs. Parker's sister Emelyn.
    - Courcy, Marquis de, to Peter Parker, n.d.
      In French.
    - Courcy, Marquis de, Macao, to Peter Parker, 1846 February 2
    - Dana, Richard P., to Peter Parker, 1847 January 12
  - Correspondence, E-G (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Everett, Edward, to Peter Parker, n.y. May 22
    - Everett, Edward, to Peter Parker, 1843 May 29
    - Everett, Edward, to Peter Parker, 1854 May 30
    - Field, Kate, to Mrs. Harriet Parker, 1868 April 30
    - Frelinghuysen, Frederick T., Washington, D.C., to Peter Parker, 1877 April 5
    - Gagliuffi, G. B., Tripoli, to Peter Parker, 1858, March 17
    - [Gill] Peter Parker to Theodore Gill, Washington, D.C., 1874 February 14
      Parker's response to "the doctrine of evolution."
    - Goertz [?], Count de, Calcutta, to Peter Parker, 1847 January 2
    - Gurley, R[alph] R[andolph], to Peter Parker, 1841 May 28
  - Correspondence, H-I (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Halford, Henry, Sir, to Peter Parker, 1841 May 1
    - Halford, Henry, Sir, to Peter Parker, 1841 May 8
    - Halford, Henry, Sir, to Peter Parker, 1841 June
    - Halford, Henry, Sir, to Dr. Kidd, Oxford, 1841 July 5
      Introducing Peter Parker.
    - Hall, Newman, to Peter Parker, n.d.
    - Hall, Newman, to Peter Parker, n.y. December 16
    - Henry, Joseph, to Peter Parker, 1869 January 16
  - Correspondence, J-L (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Jenks, William, Boston, to Peter Parker, 1838 Sepember 21
    - Julien, Stanislas, Paris, to Marc Wilks, 1841 June 24
      Letter in French addressed to Marc Wilks, Paris, asking Wilks to accompany him to translate from English when he meets Parker. Julien was a French expert on Chinese literature.
    - Kingsley, Henry Coit, Yale College, to Peter Parker, 1872 May 1
      Treasurer of Yale thanks Parker for contribution to the Woolsey Fund.
    - "Kwang Gen Fung" [?] to Peter Parker, version 1, 1846 January 4
      English translations of a letter to Parker congratulating him on his appointment from the Lieutenant Governor of Canton. May be Huang En-t'ung or Huang Entong, ca. 1800-ca. 1882.
    - "Kwang Gen-Fung" [?] to Peter Parker, version 2, 1846 January 4
    - "Kwang Gen-Fung" [?] to Peter Parker, version 3, 1846 January 4
    - Peter Parker to "Kwang Gen Fung" [?] (copy), 1846 March 25
    - Lagrené, Théodose de, Macao, to Peter Parker, 1845 December 7
      In French. Also contemporary translation into English.
    - Lagrené, Théodose de, Macao, to Peter Parker (English), 1845 December 7
    - Lagrené, Théodose de, Macao, to Peter Parker, 1846 January 8
    - Lagrené, Théodose de, Macao, to Peter Parker (English), 1846 January 8
    - Lawrence, Amos, to Dr. [Thomas] Sewall, n.d.
      "Dr. Sewall at Mr Choates."
  - Correspondence, M-P (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Maclean, John, Princeton, to Peter Parker, 1882 February 14
    - Maclean, John, Princeton, to Peter Parker, 1884 April 29
    - Macao, Governor of, to Peter Parker, 1856 January 18
    - Mai, F. T. [?], Canton, to Peter Parker, 1855 July 8
    - Monita, J. [?], Berkeley, California, to Peter Parker, n.d.
      Includes a card written in Japanese.
    - Neesima, Joseph H .[?], Kioto, Japan, to Dr. and Mrs. Parker, 1885 May 26
    - Page, Charles G., to Harriet Parker, 1856 June 14
    - Park, James D., Canton, to Peter Parker, 1851 October 14
    - Parkes, Harry, to Peter Parker, 1856 February 26
  - Correspondence, Q-S (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Quincy, Josiah, to Peter Parker, 1830 October 2
      Rev. Josiah Quincy, President of Harvard, on requirements for transfer to Harvard from another college.
    - Reed, Andrew, Rev., to Peter Parker, 1837 August 4
    - Riddel, Samuel H., Boston, to Peter Parker, 1847 April 26
    - [Ruschenberger] Harriet Parker to Dr. W. S. W. Ruschenberger (copy), 1849 April 23
      The letter concerns the U.S. Government mission to China and Peter Parker. Harriet Parker transcribed a copy of a letter from P. S. Forbes, U.S. Consul to John W. Davis.
    - [Ruschenberger] Harriet Parker to Dr. W. S. W. Ruschenberger (typed transcript), 1849 April 23
      Later typed transcript of above letter misdated April 24, 1849.
    - Sewall, Louis, to Dr. Thomas Sewall (copy), 1831 September
      With pages in Parker's hand related to the death of Rebecca Sewall in 1870.
    - Seymour, Michael, Sir, H.M. Ship Calcutta, Hong Kong, 1857 July 1
      Will not be able to dine with "His Excellency, the American Minister" on July 4.
    - Sherman, William, T., General, to Peter Parker, 1873 February 13
      Includes envelope. On the Smithsonian art collection.
    - Sigourney, Lydia. H, Washington, D.C., to Peter Parker, 1847 February 15
    - Sigourney, Lydia H., Hartford, to Peter Parker, 1849 November 14
    - Sigourney, Lydia H, Hartford, to Peter Parker, 1853 January 11
    - Silliman, Benjamin, Medical Department of Yale College, to Peter Parker, 1881 June 28
    - Smith, E. Goodrich, to Peter Parker, 1860 August 18
    - [Smith, Herbert E.] Harriet Parker, Washington, D.C., to Herbert E. Smith [Yale University School of Medicine], 1887 December 29
      Herbert E. Smith was Dean of the Medical School from 1885 to 1910. Mrs. Parker thanks him for the photographs and information on Peter Parker' collection of urinary calculi, and regrets that Parker is too ill to reply himself. Letter given to the Historical Library by Lottie G. Bishop, 1960.
    - [Smith, Herbert E.] Harriet Parker, Washington, D.C., to Herbert E. Smith [Yale University School of Medicine], 1890 March 22
      She will be shipping "two boxes containing paintings of surgical cases operated on by Dr. Parker in China." Letter given to the Historical Library by Lottie G. Bishop, 1960.
    - Stevens, George B., to Mrs. Harriet Parker, 1895 September 10
    - Stewart, J. C., to Peter Parker, n.d.
    - Stewart, J. C., Macao, to Peter Parker, 1836 October 24
  - Correspondence T-Z (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Tanaka-Fujimaro, Tokyo, to Peter Parker, 1877 April 5
    - "Tartar Lady" (Nuon, Ta-taou [?]) to Mrs. Harriet Parker, 1849 September 25
      Chinese and contemporary English translation.
    - "Tsi Yeng" to James Biddle (copy), 1846 April 22
      May be Chi Ying.
    - "Tsi Yeng" to Peter Parker, 1847 July 4
    - [Tsi Yeng] Peter Parker to "Tsi Yeng", 1848 March 8
    - Vaughn, John, Philadelphia, to Peter Parker, 1841 September 12
    - Washburn, E. A., to Peter Parker, 1871 June 4
    - [Webster] Peter Parker, Washington, D.C., to Daniel Webster, 1841 January 30
      On the desirability of sending an Embassy to China.
    - Whitney, William Dwight, New Haven, to Peter Parker, 1869 November 15
      Whitney was Professor of Sanskrit and Comparative Philology at Yale. Includes copy of Parker's draft reply
    - [Whitney] Parker's presentation in New Haven on a set of Chinese scrolls included in the Whitney letter, 1869
      Draft manuscript included with the above Whitney letter.
    - [Wood, W. M.] Peter Parker, Washington, D.C., to W. M. Wood, M.D., 1859 April 27
      Parker would be happy to receive a copy of Wood's recent book about China. Letter purchased from Henry Schuman, February 1945. The book may be William Maxwell Wood, Fankwei; or, The San Jacinto in the seas of India, China, and Japan (New York, 1859).
    - [Wood, W. M.] Peter Parker, Washington, D.C., to W. M. Wood, M.D., U.S.N., 1859 August 25
      Parker's reactions to Wood's historical and autobiographical book on China. Letter purchased from Henry Schuman, February 1945.
    - Woods, Daniel B., Philadelphia, to Peter Parker, 1847 February 22
    - "Yu Chang, foo" [?] to Peter Parker, n.d.
  - Letters from unidentified senders (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letter from unidentified sender 1, 1846 November 17
    - Letter from unidentified sender 2, 1856 November 24
    - Letter from unidentified sender 3, 1871 May 30
    - Letter from unidentified sender 4, n.y. August 28
    - Envelope possibly from the French minister, 1846 January 8
      See Lagrené, Théodose de, Macao, to Peter Parker, January 8, 1846, Folder 18.
  - William L. Marcy, US Secretary of State to the Emperor of China, letter in Chinese, 1855 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Identifiied by a patron as a letter to the emperor of China by the Secretary of State William L. Marcy about the designation of Peter Parker as American Commissioner to China.
- Journals, 2.